Hello, welcome to the Robotics Tech
podcast episode number 11. Today we got
a very special one for you because this
is our first guest. His name is Bryce
Chanchato and he's working on an
actuator. So we're going to go very deep
on this topic. My name is Oscar.
>> And my name is Leo. So we are with Bryce
Chanchato today. He's designing an
actuator that behaves like a human
joint. How are you doing today, Bryce?
>> I am doing great. It's it's great to be
on call with you guys.
>> Yeah, it's great to have you. We are
super excited to learn more about it.
Can you tell us a little bit about your
background first?
>> Sure. So right now I am a student
attending a university called Kennesaw
State based out of Georgia. Um
outside of my studies, I have started a
few startups. Uh one of them was around
a kind of autonomous car kit that you
could install in your car allowing it to
drive by itself kind of like comma AI.
Uh the other one was this exoskeleton
you could wear that could provide
resistance training. A long story short,
I'm no longer doing those and I'm, you
know, kind of working on this one right
now where I'm developing the Orbit
Actuator and I've been doing this
for quite a while now. The very first uh
iteration of this tech was developed
back in 2021 um and I've just kind of
been chugging since.
>> I'm going to dive a little deeper into
actuators fundamentals before we get to
your product. So if I had to summarize
it, I would say that actuators are the
muscles of a robot, right? Would you
agree with that?
>> Absolutely.
>> Good. So we are on a good start here.
Okay. So modern electric robot motors,
they can hit three to seven kilowatts
per kilograms while a human muscle can
only hit 0.3 kilowatts. So in a
nutshell, that means that a robot would
out strength you by several order of
magnitude. So don't get into a fight
against a robot. An actuator is an
essential part of a robot because it is
a component that converts stored energy
into force, torque, or displacements.
You could frame it as a robot needs
sensors to perceive the world and then
it needs actuator to interact with the
world. I like to present actuators in
like three levels of classification.
First of them would be the type. Uh so
we have hydraulic actuators who push
something with pressurized oil or
pressurized water. They are by far the
most powerful. They are usually pretty
large but not really precise. In between
you get pneumatic actuator. It's the
same pushing mechanism except you do it
with air instead of a liquid like oil.
It's mostly used in industry and
automotive right now. It's less powerful
but more precise than hydraulic. And
then we get electric. They are extremely
efficient and they became basically the
standard right now for robotics. At
least for humanoids. I'm I'm not quite
sure about the rest. So the second level
of classification would be motion
output. So you get rotary that delivers
torque and linear that delivers force.
Do you want like rotary force or do you
want linear force basically. And third
classification is transmission
architecture. So you get the harmonic
drive which is more precise, more stiff,
more torque dense but is not back
drivable. And then you also have quasi
direct drive which has a larger diameter
and it's mostly used in like if I had to
summarize it in a nutshell. Of course
there are exceptions. The way I
understand your product Bryce is that
it's a new level three architecture. So
it's a new transmission architecture but
with like a level two promise. Would you
say Would you say it's correct?
>> I'd say that's accurate. Yeah.
>> Nice. Nice.
So can you tell us a little bit more
about your new type of actuator then?
>> Yeah. So um I dubbed it the Orbit
Actuator and how I view it is uh you
know, you're referring to these things
as like a level two. I call them
primitives. You know, linear and rotary
they're both primitives. They both kind
of serve as the building blocks for
pretty much every robotic system if they
want to move. But you know, if they want
to recreate uh these robots, if you're
trying to recreate the motion that you
see like a human body, but at the
shoulder, the hips, or the wrists and
the ankle, that's not single-axis
motion. It's three axes, right? So,
you've got pitch, yaw, and roll. Now,
what engineers typically do is they'll
take the single-axis uh actuators that
you have like an electric motor
typically, and they'll stack them on top
of each other. So, you'll take a single
axis that'll represent the pitch, and
then you'll put another actuator on a
different plane. This one will represent
the yaw, and it will spin independent of
that first motor, and then you'll take a
third motor and stack it on top of the
second motor, and that'll be the roll.
And there's other ways to do it. Mostly,
they use like linear actuators in tandem
with Heim joints or universal joints.
But, there's a lot of issues that come
with those designs. Primarily, to do
with like distal mass. Because most of
these systems stack It's called a serial
stack of actuators. Stack these
actuators in such a way, you have to
support the weight of each consecutive
motor down this chain. Doing so really
reduces the efficiency of these systems.
It adds a lot of problems in terms of
wiring. Uh kind of limits the range of
motion. It's harder to cool these
because, you know, every single motor is
moving relative to every other motor.
And they're really kind of complicated
to construct, especially in humanoids
when, you know, a humanoid is basically
an assembly of like a dozen or so of
these stacks of actuators. And all that
being said,
you know, I thought it would be a good
idea to create an actuator that, instead
of relying on the status quo or what
engineers usually rely on to create
these multi-axis joints, to to make an
actuator that actually functions like,
you know, your hips or your shoulders.
Or to create one that moves spherically
like a ball joint. And that's that's
exactly what this actuator does. And
I've got a bunch of different ones that
I can show off later. Hopefully, that
answers your question. Yeah, definitely.
So, you're kind of merging all these
steps into one, basically, right? Pretty
much. We've taken what what normally
require uh tens of components and
removed all the inefficiencies that
comes with that and just kind of bundle
it up into a single package that's easy
to integrate into any sort of robotic
system.
>> Yeah, and just yesterday I saw an
interview with the founder of 1X and he
made a good argument. He said, "We want
to be as close to the human as possible
with everything that we have on our
robots because eventually it will make
it much easier." He was talking about
skin resistance and all these like minor
things, but he he somehow made the
argument that only this will ultimately
also allow them to train on video
because videos is usually like humans,
how they actually work kind of, you
know, and move in space and stuff like
that. I don't know what he was actually
going for there, but uh it kind of
reminded me of that because uh
sometimes, you know, technology is
making it more complicated or diverting
a lot from the actual human, right? To
some degree. It's so that's necessary
until someone comes up like you and
thinks like, "Hey, maybe we can do it."
So,
I think that's cool.
>> Yeah, thank you.
Um no, I I'm I'm kind of in his boat, I
think. I think if you're going to try
and adopt this biomimetic mindset to
develop these humanoids or these robot
dogs, you should be using components
that address these kind of developed
systems that you see in robotics and try
to like optimize them to be more like
the systems you're trying to mimic,
right? So, I totally get his point and I
totally agree.
>> Yeah. What's like your take when it
comes to the competition, how they are
doing it and how how you see this this
actuator actually coming into into
reality maybe?
>> Yeah, so I think there's like two sides
in terms of competition. Uh like we've
kind of discussed already, there's
status quo, which is like stacking
actuators on top of each other to create
all the multiple axes that you need in
order to
mimic the motion that you see in
biological systems. And then the other
side are
uh there's a lot of novel uh designs in
academia that try and create this
motion. I think one of them is called
the Abenix joint. That's I don't know if
you guys have seen it. I know it has
like millions of views on YouTube, but
it's a spherical gear that kind of
rotates um like this, but it's it's
limited in its range of motion by this
socket
that the ball sits in, and it's also
requires four motors to actuate 3° of
freedom, and the torque is also
significantly limited just strictly
because of the geometry of the gear
teeth. Just to clarify, the question was
like how do we integrate into the the
market in reference to the current
adopted technologies?
>> Yeah, I mean just like where would you
see it? Because sometimes they have
humanoids for example that uh are pretty
open, right? You can almost modularly
adapt them, and maybe I'll I'll put my
actuator technology on top of it, or
have you already implemented it in the
humanoid? I just want to grasp like
where this is like standing.
>> So, there's quite a lot of places that I
could see it being integrated. Because
it functions like a ball joint, you
could see it being used in any kind of
joint that's trying to mimic the
spherical geometry you might see in, you
know, like a person. Shoulders is a big
one, wrists, uh hips, ankles, even
necks, and like the waist, you know.
Waist is important, one so you could
bend over, but two so you can kind of
move your center of gravity around a
humanoid. So, having those additional
degrees of freedom is really helpful for
something like that when especially when
these humanoids are going to be used
primarily in factories, lifting things
up, you got to adjust that center of
gravity to get like better grips
on these things. Um outside of
humanoids, I think it would be
incredibly useful in things like robotic
arms. Because the same issues you run
into with humanoids in terms of these
serial stacks of actuators, you run into
in robotic arms. So, you could reduce
the the distal mass of all these systems
by using something like this, you know?
You could have the three axes of motion
without having the weight and the motors
that you'd see normally. And then
there's lots of other ones you could see
being used in like gimbal-like
technology, a lot of defense tech, uh
drone tech. One of the cool examples
that I think would be really cool is in
prosthetics. In prosthetics, you're not
going to see anything that really moves
above one axis, specifically for like a
wrist. In fact, what you'll see a
majority of the time is a wrist that
won't even move. You'll see a hand
that's kind of just
affixed to a forearm or the residual
limb. So, if you could design a
prosthetic around this actuator, kind of
adopts the same form factor as you'd see
like an upper forearm and a wrist
already. Um you would enable these
people to have all three degrees of
freedom that they lost, enabling them to
kind of regain the functionality that
they lost. Uh I think that would be
really cool. And there's plenty of
others I could keep naming.
>> Okay. Maybe another question that
touches on that. Are some people already
using similar technology or where you
see this already or is no one else using
this or implementing this in any shape
so far?
>> So, the closest I've seen in industry is
this joint that has a very similar name
to mine and I was not aware of the name
prior. It's called the Orbita. Or
originally it was created by I think it
was Mark Rosheim or Rosenheim or
whatever his name is, but it was adopted
by Palin Robotics and then they were
bought by Hugging Face, I think is the
name of the company.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah. Um and they use I I think it's
called a parallel spherical actuator
wherein they have all these linkages
that have kind of this spherical
geometry and they come up and meet like
a at a platform. Kind of like a Stewart
platform, but way more fancy and way
harder to manufacture. But it does have
this kind of motion, but it's really
limited in its range of motion and the
torque that it can produce. So, my
actuator has a hemispherical work
envelope.
So, anywhere within a hemisphere it can
move. But with the Orbita, it's limited
to kind of a conical work envelope. So,
anything past let's say like 45°. It
just can't move past that threshold.
>> Mhm, that's not much.
>> I I think it really kind of limits any
adoption that it's had. And I think the
the last one that's vaguely akin to this
is used in the DaVinci robot uh for
their little tiny baby hands that they
use to do the surgery. They've got a
really really wicked cool wrist
mechanism that relies on the three or
four universal joints with threaded rods
attached at the base of them and you can
vary the length of these threaded rods
to vary the angle of these universal
joints to kind of create this motion.
And it's really it's a stiff design, but
you know, there's a reason you only see
it in very very small scale mechanisms.
>> Yeah, and with the DaVinci I think Leo
and just in one of our last episodes
talked about it how they actually
reproduce some of the capabilities of it
with the Unitree and teleoperation. Oh,
>> Oh, yeah. Gallbladder gallbladder
removal.
>> Yeah, so in a nutshell it's like you
know, the
the DaVinci robot it has like the robot
that operates on the patient on one side
and on the other side there is a
teleoperation device which is like an
entire booth. The surgeon is almost
getting in inside of, you know? And they
have control with their hand with their
feet and they have an entire like field
of view that takes their entire head for
like an immersive view of what they're
doing. They get this teleoperation
controller and they use two Unitree
robots to operate on a big instead of
using the DaVinci and it works.
>> And it's pretty impressive. Yeah,
because the difference in pricing is
several of the off magnitudes as well. I
think a DaVinci machine is close to $2
million as well.
And
the two Unitree
humanoids by like 15 or 20k each.
>> Right. I I mean, I could see that it'd
be being adopted across the medical
industry. I don't know if Unitree would
be used for that anymore though because
of the FC something that just happened
the other day. Unfortunately, uh that's
a whole other topic. I don't know if we
want to dive into that or not.
>> We are pretty open. What is your take on
this recent ban?
>> So, I'm a bit conflicted. Like, I
understand the argument from the
security perspective, but I also think
So, it's almost like anti-capitalist in
a way. I think you're getting rid of
competition just to support the humanoid
companies that are in America, which I
understand. You want to be able to
maintain uh the industry that's kind of
developing in America since it's a
little less developed than what's in
China right now because China is
supporting a lot of the companies that
are developing these humanoids. I don't
know. I don't love it, and I don't hate
it. It has its upsides and downsides.
It's probably the least direct answer I
could give, I think.
Yeah. What do you guys think?
>> I I agree. I think it's very new, so we
will see how it play out, you know, all
these market dynamics that come into
place. It's not like you can anticipate
everything. It's very similar to the GPU
thing where they are not sending GPUs to
China kind of, but this time it's kind
of like the other way around a bit. And
there's always these other layers as
well where it's okay, you're blocking
the humanoid, but you're blocking also
this type of component. Maybe you need
this one from China. This one comes
here. Maybe there's going to be open
models coming there, so I think it will
be very interesting how broad this will
eventually get. And hopefully not too
broad because eventually I think I mean,
we're just better off signing altogether
and not getting overtaken by some some
some weird AI, right?
>> Right.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, I personally think competition is
for losers until someone outcompetes
you, and I think that's kind of what's
happening, unfortunately.
>> Mhm.
>> So, I think it is I mean, I understand
the move, uh even though, you know, I'm
not American, so it's easy for me to
say, but I also think it's a bit sad
because I think research will suffer the
most from it, definitely. Uh because
there is no equivalent of Unitree in the
US right? You cannot get
a humanoid that's good enough for 20k.
It just doesn't exist. I've seen posts
about 1X who wants to develop a humanoid
platform for developers.
>> 1X is like 20k just a little bit up,
right? So it's kind of competitive.
>> There's also something else because I
mean
I don't remember the name of the guy or
the startup but I I saw the guy who has
a startup in the US who does a robot OS
kind of that's
100% safe when it comes to security
matters. And he says that if you run
your Unitree robot with his OS, you are
100% sure there is no Chinese backdoor
still active in the robot. So if there
are options like this to run the Chinese
robot safely on US soil, then it becomes
100% and you know, anti-competition move
not a security risk. So security risk is
just there to wrap it up a little bit
nicely. So yeah,
I don't know what to think of it. I
think since it's mostly cheap robots,
the people who will suffer from it are
the ones who actually needed the most.
So research, academia and so on
unfortunately.
>> But maybe back to your actuator. But
yeah, again it makes no sense. I mean we
talked about some of your advantages.
Maybe there are more that you haven't
mentioned yet and also maybe limitations
where you see okay, it's a great tech
that I developed with my heart but maybe
there's also some things where I would
say okay, maybe maybe this is where I
can make it better.
>> So obviously one of the advantages
you've got that lower distal mass. So
the way that this actual works
uh
is you have this joint up top that's for
the most part hollow, right? It's really
just a shell.
Uh you can kind of see through it. It's
got a through hole.
Um but all of the motion that happens up
here is a result of what's happening
down here.
So what we have here
are three
electric motors. But instead of being
serially stacked, these motors are
stacked in parallel. So, they all rest
concentrically. They don't move relative
to one another. They stay fixed. And
each of these motors corresponds with a
different axis of motion of bottom.
So, this top motor controls
this what I call the lower hemisphere.
Some people call it the clam shell cuz
it it kind of looks like a seashell.
Then the second motor rotates the upper
hemisphere like this. And the third
motor right here rotates the effector
like so.
Um so, you know, you get the benefit of
all the motors are down here. You don't
have to worry about that weight there.
Additionally, we have this through hole.
And what the through hole allows you to
do is route wires through the center of
the actuator without sacrificing the
range of motion of the system. So, in a
lot of humanoids or in a lot of robotic
systems, you have to route wires to each
of the motors or like down this chain.
And those wires can limit the range of
motion and
because of the way that this through
hole works,
uh the wires go straight to the origin
point of this joint. So, you don't need
to worry about them getting tangled or
anything like that. They just move uh
freely as this thing rotates around. Uh
because it has this lower distal mass,
you also have like lower reflected
inertia. I think it also has like better
packaging. It's pretty modular, easy to
integrate. Uh some things that I have
yet to really find out is one, how well
does it work in sim-to-real? I think,
and this is based on conversations I've
had with this guy named Animesh Garg. He
helped develop uh Isaac Lab back when he
worked at Nvidia. Uh he thinks it would
be great. But, you know, that's just
word of mouth. We'd have to really test
it.
Um so, I hope he's right. Uh but, we'll
see. Additionally, and I think I already
mentioned this, it takes what would
normally take 10, 20, 30 components,
mushes it all into one thing. You can
imagine how much easier it would be on
the engineers designing these robots to
just buy a single actuator that does all
the work of these three actual the three
actuators normally that would have to be
attached with brackets to one another.
You got to deal with all the bearings
and all the electronics and all the
wires and it's just kind of a nightmare.
And this one's a little more niche, but
in in those typical systems what you run
into a lot of times, and this is why
Boston Dynamics redesigned the Atlas
again, is pinch points. This does not
have a single pinch point in the design.
So, you won't have to worry about uh any
of those. So, it's really really nice
when interacting with with human you
know, humanoids are kind of designed to
be able to interact with humans, so you
want to reduce as much danger as
possible. Oh, um in terms of sealing the
joint, uh normally it's kind of hard to
like weather proof a lot of these
multi-axis systems. Uh the way the joint
design, it's very easy to do that. It
comes with lots of different
configurations as well. And I'll I'll
get to the downsides in a minute. I just
got to go through the benefits first.
So, we've got the the three-axis one
here. Obviously, it's got the pitch,
yaw, and roll.
Um and then uh we've also got this
two-axis version. I created this as
consequence of a conversation I had with
Jonathan Hurst. He's one of the founders
of Agility Robotics. Uh he was looking
for
a better way to design the wrist in his
robot, and I showed him the three-axis
version, and he said, "That's really
cool, but we already have a third axis
or the pitch kind of embedded in the
forearm of the robot. Um we don't need
that extra axis. It would just be
redundant."
So, that's what this one is.
Well, so it it has just two axes of
motion.
Well, not this one in particular, the
one I'm referring to uh the lower
hemisphere's fixed and it has an end
effector in the upper hemisphere that
spins, but that's beside the point. And
then this one is a four-axis version
of the actuator.
Um it has the pitch, yaw, and roll that
you normally see, um but it also has two
independently uh rotating end effectors.
So, what's cool about this is in
addition to having those three axes you
normally see, say you want to stick an
end effector on the end of this.
Uh instead of having to take a motor,
stick it on the end, you know, you got
to deal with the additional mass that
comes with that motor that would be used
to actuate the end effector.
Uh you can use the motor that's already
embedded at the base of the actuator to
actuate the end effector. And I've got
an example of that.
Uh I think I had sent Leo the video.
It's of this robotic dog that I thrown
together.
Uh where one axis is used to actuate the
shoulder and the other one is used to
actuate the elbow.
Yeah.
And
all of it's controlled just with one
unit. So, it's got this four-axis leg
just with one actuator, which I think is
really cool. And then
I know I mentioned this earlier. Uh
there's, you know, generally thermal
management problems with the way these
three-axis, four-axis joints are usually
designed in humanoids. It's really
obvious if you've ever watched the races
that China hosts. I think the winner of
this year's race was the was the guys
that figured out how to do the thermal
management in their robots. But a
majority of them hadn't figured it out
yet. And I say they figured it out, it
doesn't mean that it doesn't look crazy.
You know, you've got all these pipes and
stuff sticking out of every single joint
of this robot. But because with the the
orbit actuator, all the motor's down
here, if you're housing it or you've got
it in your your your robot, well, all
you got to cool are the motors back
here, right? You don't have to worry
about cooling any of the motion that's
happening at the joint. So, you don't
have to worry about all these moving
cooling components. And then of course,
outside of humanoids is lots and lots of
different applications. I'm viewing it
as like a third primitive that can be
used as a platform technology to develop
all other kinds of systems.
Now, in terms of downsides, and these
are things that I'm currently figuring
out, so I don't think they're permanent
downsides. One, I'm working on the DFM
of the design. Right now, it's plastic.
Now, I have good news. I recently
started working with two really
incredible people.
Um one of them is Peter Middleton. He Um
he runs a company called Bishop
Aerospace. They do a lot of uh stuff
with like military. He's going to be
helping
with the DFM and like manufacturing the
first metal prototype and potentially
demo units down the line. In addition to
that, I'm working with Tyler Shudester.
He runs Metamorphis Technologies, but
prior to that, he was the former head of
motor design or motor manufacturing at
1X.
So, he's going to be working on the
motors that are going inside the
actuator. And he's also helping with the
rest of the internal design to help fix
all the little tiny issues inside of the
actuator. And one of the questions that
I get in terms of downsides is like, how
does the singularity work in the
actuator? And you know, that's something
that's present in pretty much every
single multi-axis system. And how we're
going to get around it is mostly just
through software, right? So, either it's
like a path optimization thing or you
know, you just avoid the very very pop
point of the joint and you won't have to
deal with any of the issues that you
normally see like
singularities in multi-axis systems.
Now, you guys tell me if you see any
downsides that are like blatantly
obvious that I'm completely not
mentioning. I would love to hear what
you guys think.
>> I mean, I don't see like really like
downsides, but just one question that
just came up to me when you're talking
about this collaboration with on these
other guys. Do you have like a team that
with with some co-founders or are you
like on your own now or is it more like
an open collaboration or what is like
the setup right now?
>> So, Tyler and Peter are both getting a
little bit of equity for their help. I
did have co-founders at one point. One
of them is named Nikhil. He was the P in
CNPR&D. The name is tentative. I'll get
to work on changing it eventually. He
wanted to go focus on his career and no
bad blood or anything between us.
I totally respect the decision. I get
it.
Startups are hard.
And he was trying to balance his day job
with this and it was just surely a
nightmare. And then we had another guy
that was in sales, but we just decided
you know, it's too early. So, there's no
real point in keeping him. So, right now
it's just me. And you could count Tyler
and you could count Peter. They they've
been great so far.
>> Yeah.
>> And a question back to the downsides. I
mean I'm just like wondering, okay, can
you scale this infinitely or is there
like a limit? I mean you said already
materials. I guess there will there are
some implications if you use something
else than what you're currently using.
>> Surprisingly not okay. So the the
scaling the actuator is not that hard.
It's the only real limitation is the
size of the motors and the size of the
bearings we're using. Assuming you can
accommodate those, then you can make it
as small as the knuckles in your finger
if you really wanted to or as big as the
the joints that you'll see in the giant
Yaskawa robot arms putting together
cars. And I think it would just it would
be just as effective across those
different sizes. Additionally, this is a
different way to look at the scale of
it. Because of the way it's designed
it's very easy to add additional degrees
of freedom to the joint. So you could
theoretically keep adding additional
motors on the bottom and then it would
correspond with additional axes of
motion
up here. So you could
have a six seven axis robot arm wherein
all of the motors are mounted at the
base and the arm itself weighs almost
nothing. Um but it has the torque of
what you would normally see in like a a
big hefty robotic arm.
And it wouldn't have any of the
downsides. I'm sure it would have its
own
you know, demerits in some capacity if
you have this many motors stacked like
this, but I you wouldn't have to deal
with the the typical downsides of like a
multi-axis arm.
>> Yeah, for sure. I I think the base
mounted mounted motors design is like
the smartest thing about it to me. But
I'm curious. You don't seem to
communicate on torque on your specs.
Yeah. Is it intentional or
>> So um that is really just a consequence
of the motors we're using. Um for the
sake of prototyping we're just using
three off-the-shelf motors we bought
from China. It's a big hollow shaft
motor that we buy from Steadywood.
Um
Each of those, I think they have a peak
torque of 10 Newton meters a pop.
Uh right now it's all direct drive.
There's no real downside in terms of
loss and torque. So, the gears are
while they may not be the most
manufacturable at the moment, they're
not really that inefficient. So, you
don't have to worry about the torque
dipping or anything. But, it is pretty
easy to integrate reducers into the
design. It's just a matter of sticking
reducers on on top of each of these
motors. And the reduction is going to
transfer over to the the motion up top.
So, right now
each axis has 10 Newton meters of
torque, but Tyler's cooking something up
that's going to be really crazy. So, I'm
looking forward to getting a spec sheet
out there to everyone that wants one.
And there are a lot of people that want
one. I promise.
>> That's very cool. Yeah, I would be very
very good to see that. So, yeah, I
looked a little bit into the history of
spherical actuators and there are
precedents actually. You probably know
about them. So, there is a professor at
Georgia Tech. So, he's pretty close to
you.
>> Yeah.
>> He's called Kok-Meng Lee and he has done
research on permanent magnets spherical
motors. And I've also seen that Carnegie
Mellon has a history of doing spherical
induction motors. So, what I understand
is that
these motors they are, you know, they
use magnets, you know, to activate.
While yours used geared ball joints.
It's important to underline because I
mean we are going to display that for
the people who watch us, but for people
who listen to us,
you actually have gears inside your
actuators and that's what make it move
and that's what makes it powerful,
right?
>> Correct. Correct. Yeah, we've got um a
series of bevel gears and a ring gears
and that allow the motion to happen.
>> I see. And so, my question with that is
you have three motors in, you know, in
the base. Does it make it as many points
of failure? What does serviceability
look like? Is it better, worse, or the
same than having the three stacked
actuators that you mentioned that
already exist in traditional humanoid
design? What do the torque?
>> So, you're saying like is it as good as
what's on the market, basically?
>> not as good as good. Not I would say as
reliable. And when it comes to
serviceability, for example, if one
motor breaks, does it break the entire
actuator or only one degree of motion?
Things like that.
>> The actuator is incredibly easy to
service, so then I would say more easy
to service than the typical multi-axis
joints you see.
In order to say swap a motor out,
uh all you really need to do is is take
this cap off right here, and then take
these uh bolts off that go around the
diameter of this chassis.
You could take the motor off, swap it
for a new one,
and that's all. Uh every single one of
these motors are rotates independently
of one another in relation to the three
axes of motion of this joint up top. So,
you don't need to worry about a single
motor destroying the entire actuator.
Now, if for whatever reason all three
motors decide to
uh explode, you can very easily swap out
the entire unit for another one because
the design is incredibly modular. And
then I think the other part of Leo's
question, how many points of failure
does it have? Now, I don't have an exact
answer to this,
uh but I can tell you that it is less
than what you would see in a typical
serial axis joint. In terms of the I
know you're referencing the permanent
magnet spherical motors. Those ones are
really cool. They have quite a few
issues though. One is it's really
difficult to
do anything that's like bearing adjacent
with those. So, it kind of needs to
float right in the center of this
spherical array of magnets or
electromagnetic coils, which as you can
imagine causes some problems, especially
in terms of torque. And also because of
this super complex array of
electromagnets, you run into a lot of
distortions with the the magnetic field
that you're using to control the system.
So, I'm not confident in the precision
of those, especially under load. And
lastly, you really run into a limitation
in terms of the the work envelope of
these
um permanent magnet spherical motors.
Because it it is a ball inside of a
socket, and the socket is these
electromagnets, you're limited to the
size of the socket, right? Especially if
you want to entirely encapsulate this
ball to get the best motion you can get
out of it. So, it's it's kind of it's
conical, right? The work envelope is
conical. So,
it's not super practical. And also,
they're heavy as hell. I mean, I don't
know if you've seen them, but you're
going to put them on the screen, I'm
assuming.
Um they are enormous.
Uh and I don't know how practical they
would ever be in any actual mechanical
system. Now, I don't doubt in the future
there's going to be some genius that's
able to figure it out, but, you know, I
haven't seen anything yet.
>> Yeah. I'm guessing that's why they
remained a research topic and they never
really made their way into the industry.
And this leads me to another question,
which is would you
do the entire production in the US, or
would you have to source some parts from
China or from Japan? Because, you know,
we talked about the recent trade ban on
Chinese humanoids in the US. Also,
recently Standard Bots raised 200
million. And Standard Bots wants to
manufacture their entire robot arms
end-to-end in the US. So, on which side
of the debate would you stand on that?
>> Ooh. Ooh, that's a good question.
You know, I'm not sure yet. Because the
design has yet to be or because we don't
have a product completely developed yet,
right? Uh it's still in the prototype
phase. The final components that we need
in order to design the product have yet
to be decided. So, I could totally see
it being either which way. Now, does
that mean we'll go with China? I don't
know. I know I've been talking with a
few other companies like Schaeffler is a
big one that I've been talking with.
They're based in Germany, right? Uh so,
we might end up sourcing components from
them. So, I don't know. There's There's
a good chance for either one.
Now, I see the benefits of both. I also
see the negatives of both. Working in
America, obviously,
you want to foster the industry that's
kind of been
>> Yeah.
>> demolished by China over I mean, more
years than I've been alive, right? But,
also China's manufacturing capacity and
their complete breadth of components is
crazy and the price of each of those, I
mean, you can't beat it. So, if we're
arguing if if we want to scale fast,
then you would go with China. But,
there's also the risk that if you work
with China, then the FCC might throw
something in your face and completely
curtail your entire business model
and your entire production line and then
you'd be screwed. So, I'll put an
asterisk and say, "We'll figure it out.
We'll see."
>> That's a good mindset because yeah, it
becomes a structural risk for most
robotics companies right now. I mean,
for most industries in general. I mean,
my last questions around your market and
your customers. To give you an idea,
actuators are usually approximately half
the price tag of each humanoid, right?
Because they are expensive to make and
the humanoids have lots of them. So, I'm
curious about who is your your
customers? Do you want to sell your
actuators to robot manufacturers? Would
you license the architecture or would
you develop the product and hope to be
acquired? What is your mindset of that?
If you have one, maybe you are Right.
very open in your current phase.
>> So,
I don't know if there's one particular
route that we're completely dedicated
to. I think it's going to be a a
mishmash of uh several Early on, I think
the best route to go is the licensing
route.
Only so we can bring in enough capital
to sustain or to create a, you know,
manufacturing or create the
manufacturing capacity we would need in
order to sell these at scale. So, once
we do license and once we bring in some
capital, then we will do the
manufacturing in-house and then sell to
the these OEMs or these these these
component manufacturers to be used in
different kinds of systems, like the
robotic arms or the humanoids or the
robot dogs or whatever. So, it's it's
really those two at the moment. We'll
kind of see. I've I've got a bunch of
stuff cooking in the background, but
nothing's been completely fleshed out
yet. Uh there's some potential
partnerships that may end up working out
and then that would kind of decide the
course of where we would go. So, we'll
see.
>> Yeah. Can you name any partnerships you
have that you're working on or is it
like confidential?
>> Ooh.
Um that is a good question. Tell you
what, I'll I'll tell you and then I'll
let you know after the recording if you
can keep it in or not. There's one of
them, so we'll see how that goes. I was
working with My Actuator, the company,
not it's their name is weird. I was
working with them for a while, uh but
that didn't end up panning out because
they got bogged down by uh creating a
new manufacturing facility, so they were
just hellishly busy. Um so, that's
something that might be picked up again
in the future. I don't think I can say
the other ones. I'm going to be honest.
>> You probably also talked to VCs, I
guess, trying to raise capital. How how
did that go? Can you talk about that?
>> Ooh. Okay, this is a fun one. So, I have
been stuck in a chicken-and-egg
situation for quite a while. So, and
this has recently, I think, been
alleviated because of Tyler and Peter
and thank God they're helping now. But
prior, all the VCs I discussed or talked
to were of the same mind, they wanted me
to come back once I had a product,
right? You you have traction or you have
a product that we can see fully fleshed
out. We don't want to see a 3D printed
plastic thing. Like it's a really,
really cool concept. We love the idea.
But come back later.
Um [snorts]
and then I'd be like, "Okay, so I need
to develop this product." Uh what do I
need to develop a product? Money.
Uh so you can kind of see the issue here
is in order to get VC's attention, I
need something to show them that other
people can buy. But in order to make the
thing that people can buy to show the
VC's, I need money from the VC's to You
see where the problem comes?
>> Yeah.
>> Uh
Now, that isn't to say that the the VC's
were all interested in the tech cuz I
think they can all see the vision. Way I
I look at it and I think I already
discussed this is, you know, this is
this is a a new primitive.
Um there's a reason that so many people
have tried to make something like it.
And I I genuinely think that it could be
something on the scale of rotary and
linear actuators. And that that idea,
just the sheer magnitude of the
potential, really caught the eyes of
these VC's. But all of them are
incredibly risk-averse, especially in
hard tech. So, you know, that's where
that's at. We'll see.
>> But how much how much money is actually
missing? Because, I mean, do they expect
a full-fledged production line or just
like a single unit? I mean, how much
money do you need? Maybe maybe there's
someone in the audience uh who who can
support you.
>> Right, right, right. So, I
I think for just like a demo unit or
sending out demo units, I think
something in the the ballpark of like
250 would be good enough. If we wanted
to completely flesh out the design, hire
a team, maybe do like a small-scale
manufacturing, I think that's in the
ballpark of like 2 to 4 million. Just
because hard tech is so expensive. You
need that kind of capital, right? It's
not like a software company where you
can just uh have Claude, you know, vibe
code you a a website, an application.
You know, you got to pay for all of the
raw materials, you got to pay for the
motors, a lot of times you got to pay
for the tariffs, all the electronics,
uh machining costs, labor costs, all
that jazz. So, uh 250 for demos, 2 to 4
million for, you know, the whole
package, we'll say.
>> I'll figure interesting thing that you
mentioned was that you were considering
the licensing. Because of a If I
remember correctly, the founder of Neura
Robotics, you know, the German robotics
company, I think he has a very
interesting um past. Should also go to
an episode of us. He had the a similar
problem when he wanted to start the
robotics company. He had basically
nothing and um he started with licensing
as well, as far as I know. Pretty
interesting. So, I think there are many
ways and many routes that you can go
with this. And especially if the core
technology is fledged out, which it
sounds like. I mean, that's uh it's a
pretty remarkable tech and then
looks um This looks kind of satisfying
as well when you move it around, to be
honest.
>> Yeah. It's all It's got to get like a
little fidget uh thing going, right?
>> Oh, it's very own. So, it's very fun.
I'm sure I mean, I sent Leo a bunch of
videos. You could probably put those on
screens to like an ASMR thing in the
background or something. I got to
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> 14-hour uh accurate
>> [laughter]
>> So, 14-hour It's a very cool like
Twitter master class.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, that's cool.
>> Yeah, maybe going more to the general
outlook on the robotics market. What are
your predictions? Uh I don't know how
much you look at models and capabilities
in general, how much you look you look
to the left and to the right because
you're probably laser focused on your
product. But, um what do you What do you
What do you see robotics in the next 5
and next 10 years?
>> Ooh. Okay.
Um so, I'm not going to go the Elon
route and say that everybody's going to
have one in their house.
Uh I think that's ridiculous. No shade
to Elon, but I Yeah, whatever. I think
it will start dominating a lot of the
industries that rely on really menial,
almost depressing labor. And I see the
potential issues with that. Obviously,
people are not going to want to lose
their jobs, but I also see the benefit.
A lot of the dangers that are associated
with those jobs and you know, the
potential deaths that come with those
will no longer happen. Um you can weigh
that how you will. Now, in terms of it
being in the home, uh and I'm all
talking about humanoids, not just
robotics in general. I could see it
working if they really get down the
ability for it to do chores well and
consistently. Cuz fundamentally, nobody
wants to do those and they're buying the
robot to do the chores, right? They're
not buying it to take care of the
children. They're they're buying it to
do the dishes and the laundry and vacuum
the floors and whatever. And I I don't
know how soon that will be, but I
definitely know that nobody's going to
really adopt it if you're still relying
on teleoperation
for these robots in the home. I don't
know if it's just me, but that that
seems creepy. I definitely would not
want that in my house.
Um
>> yeah, we had this discussion, yeah.
>> Yeah, yeah, okay, okay. I do definitely
see it being adopted in a lot of
industries. Uh the potential's there. I
mean, this is an argument that a lot of
people say, but anywhere where humans do
labor, you could literally just drag and
drop these humanoids to do the same
thing, right?
What the time scale of that looks like,
things accelerate fast. I could see it
happening in maybe the next seven or
eight years, but I definitely think we
still have a long way to go from all the
demos that we see nowadays, which is
robots punching each other
and robots dancing and
doing the dougie to
you know, what we need to be seeing. And
to be fair, there are some companies
that have really developed, you know,
actual capacity to do meaningful tasks.
Figure did a pretty cool demo with this
robot on the assembly line.
Um I enjoyed that
several day uh escapade watching that on
on YouTube. I think Boston Dynamics is
doing a cool job. I mean, that could be
me fanboying cuz I mean, who doesn't
over Boston Dynamics? Uh but they're
working on the Hyundai facility is
really cool. Hopefully, that answers
that question. I went on a bit of a a
tangent there.
>> I think everybody's is feeling that,
especially the ones who have like some
access to this uh sector. Maybe another
one more in the uh theoretical sphere.
What do you wish people worked more on
in the robotic space? What is something
maybe that you have encountered where
you're like, "Come on. Why is nobody
doing this?" Or maybe something that you
would have considered working yourself
on and you're like, "Nah, I'll prefer
working on the actual data."
>> That is a great question. I mean, the
cop-out answer is like people should be
making better actuators. Uh but I'm not
going to say that. Uh
I I think exoskeletons have an
incredible incredible amount of
potential, especially robotic
exoskeletons, to help people that have
like disabilities or are like working
through uh health problems or anything
like that. Both in an assistive and a
resistive capacity. I mean, you could
have these exoskeletons help you walk,
help you walk again, you know, give you
back that autonomy that you lost. And
this next part is going to be based on
the whole selling point of the one
startup I did a while ago. You could
also have exoskeletons that are
resistive to your body and kind of allow
you to exercise wherever you want to be.
Uh just do a random menial task at your
house. You could wear this thing and
that would resist your motion and
basically work yourself out. It would be
like a a Bowflex. I think that's the
name of the machine. Just on your body.
I think that'd be dope.
>> There are these uh exoskeletons right
for for walking. I think that's one that
you uh get around your hips. And I think
there are two ways that you can put it.
And and one is actually resistance. And
I'm not sure if people actually use it.
And it uh still looks a bit clunky
sometimes when you see it on video. It
still like, it's not like entirely
smooth.
But, uh uh
I can see that as well. For training,
for example, or things like that. I saw
a video of a guy turning it up and
cranking up the resistance and
he was walking like like an old man,
basically. So, um but yeah, maybe he
gained some muscle.
>> Yeah. And then I guess my other answer,
and this is kind of tangential to what I
said earlier, I think prosthetics could
really use some attention from the the
robotics space. I think it hasn't had a
lot, one because it's kind of a
big monopoly that kind of dominates.
>> Definitely called Ottobock.
>> Uh they kind of dominate the industry
and they really prevent a lot of the
innovation that you would otherwise see.
Also, the industry is relatively small,
so a lot of the companies
uh are, you know, that they've got
investors and those investors want them
to go after things that bring in a lot
of money. So, these people that would
otherwise see the benefits of this
incredible innovation don't get to see
it because they're like a small group of
people. Uh so, I definitely think the
technology that's being developed in
humanoids could just as well be used in
uh the prosthetic space.
>> It's a very encouraging industry, to be
honest. Um there's so much potential
there and uh yeah. Maybe, Leo, do you
have any other questions?
>> No, I asked all the questions I wanted
to ask.
>> No, I think Bryce, that was really nice,
very insightful. I mean, we got it all,
many different topics, but of course
also getting first-hand experience with
actuators was something I think we have
to have on this channel and it's going
to be a staple on this channel. Huh,
first interview as well. Uh
>> Yeah, I'm honored. Thank you for
inviting me.
>> It was a pleasure. Thank you so much for
watching the Robotics Tech Podcast
episode 11. That was Bryce Chenchou,
Oscar, and
>> Leo.
>> Bye-bye.